so I'm here with Alexander barred the
Camille Paglia of Sweden the story
behind that was that you and I were in
Kiev Ukraine and this American guy came
up while I was talking and said that I I
was like a male Camille Paglia and I
told him was those flattery in common I
ever had in my life yeah I've already
thought of that since the first time we
spoke I've considered you to be the like
so I'm being compared to the lesbian
nature mmm you can't you kept him word
modern to being compared to the lesbian
Nietzsche can you I mean I love Camille
Paglia she's my you know besides my
girlfriend the favorite woman on the
planet so there you go so you ain't
never gotta start with a Jordan Jordan
Peterson quote today ya know I've even
printed it just to quote him absolutely
correctly as if we get this right okay
okay go for it hmm my god is the spirit
that tries to elevate B makes everything
come together makes order out of chaos
recast order when it becomes too
limiting the spirit of truth incarnate
none of that is supernatural it is to
stay what is most real okay that's
Jordan penis oh my god is the spirit
that tries to elevate be okay this is
our Astron ism and I'm not sure Jordan
Peterson is aware of that it seems that
the person or Iranian part of Asian
histories was lacking in the West's
understanding of these so we know quite
a lot about China in India and we're
overwhelmed my Chinese in India culture
knowing that their heritage is way
bigger than anything we created in the
West but it's actually the Iranian
heritage that is the most underrated one
because it connects the other two and
large parts of the history of ideas with
China and India originated in Iran and I
think it's striking that Jordan Peterson
has a quote here about his own religion
where he's actually admitting to
religion that it's existed for over
3,000 years
that is his religion so we should tell
Jordan Peterson he's disaster mm-hmm and
you and I just yeah where does he think
he's a Christian then no he's definitely
not a Christian he's an ironic Christian
he would admit to that but we can go
into that later okay but we've got a
comparing today with John for Erica who
is a friend of ours and we huge fans of
America's work if a variety is
admittedly a Western Buddhists yeah so
why don't we call today's session
Jordan Peterson the saw rostrum versus
John for varka the Buddhist very good
and I've written about ten articles
about genre baekje so far huh yeah and
I'm going through his series very
systematically as a kind of education
for myself and also and also to try to
make his message which can be kind of
overly complex more understandable to
myself and other people
yeah it is very complex it really is but
John for Varrick is formidable he's
brilliant he's a close friend a sweet
guy and he gets it right that means if
you want to go through the history of
ideas from a Western perspective
starting with axial H up until now you
can't do anything better then go through
all the 40 episodes John for variks work
on on YouTube I mean it's amazing that
he just does these very simple lectures
they're not that more technically
complicated than with you and I were
trying to do here which is kind of scary
because we're getting away with murder
because it's cheap we'll equipment as we
do but John's John's work is a great
place to start it's a good foundation
for where we want to go yeah and Jordan
who is also Canadian like you it's all
coming out of Canada right now isn't it
Jordan ease is a good contrast to to
John Farrar key too because what I've
said all along in my work with John
Soderquist is that we're interested in
the phallic vision and we're currently
writing a trilogy we published two books
we're gonna write the third book over
the next three to four years and we're
gonna call the grand narrative
you and I've discussed it at length
before him but what is lacking in the
North American perspective is this is
this lack of phallus oh this is very
important because for couple reasons
firstly it's very offensive to people
when you say that right away people just
freak out and I wanna maybe we could
talk about why that is and and also why
it's it's so important and why we're
lacking uh let's say masculine phallic
vision in the West or actually not
masculine you would say phallic is is
both feminine masculine yeah Chuck Chaka
Khan a famously these French that I was
famous said that phallus is hopefully
something men have and something women
are so in that is physiologically
speaking when a man looks at a woman is
attracted by the theme of body the
entire female bodies falling whereas
when you know women are looking to men
it's not literally the Fowler's the dick
they might be looking for but you know
they do it have sexual intercourse
obviously but women are looking for
found a character in men meaning if the
man doesn't go out there in the world
and he comes back and delivers to me why
would I pay attention to it so so it is
deeply sexual and that ties into my
critique of the current North American
discourse I mean they're wonderful
people out there I'm glad people have
discovered Benita Roy to him because
Benita Roy is a great complexity
scientist and she can explain complexity
science to people in a really smart
categorical matter
she's like the complexity scientist
Jordan Peterson know yeah people have
discovered Benita Roy John from
hurricane they certainly discovered
Jordan Peterson and we also have friends
like Jordan Hall and Dennis Specter
Berger who work out of California we
have Zachary Stein is doing formidable
work on the future of Education Greg
Henriques who's doing the interesting
Tree of Knowledge project which is
incredibly ambitious right so we have a
lot of friends in North America doing
great work at the moment while you and I
sitting here in Europe commenting on
what they're doing but what is lacking
in all of this is
sexuality it's really lucky there's some
there's a deep respect for you and
there's certainly a union revival going
on but you can't understand young
without Freud mmm you try to understand
doing without Freud you end up with
young the Contin and you end up with uh
you know a guy's popular with old ladies
and the New Age circles and and you end
up with hardly anything more than you H
2.0 at best and so the problem is you
can't escape sexuality any longer after
the Revolution of 19th century Germany
and after Nietzsche and Freud
you can't escape sexuality if you try to
you end up in a no-man's land where you
say like your fur market does you
basically say well we can't have any
utopia vicious because we know they're
incredibly dangerous yeah but you can't
intellectually honestly say you must not
have something because they're afraid of
its consequences mm-hmm because that
means you've already made it you're
bullshitting yeah well you gotta go you
gotta go everywhere if you're in search
of the truth wigs is with Jordan
Peterson does Jordan Peterson is the
only one of the North American still
who's pointing out that a phallic
direction is needed
we gotta phonic direction we're not
gonna get anywhere okay when I one of
the things I appreciate about rebecky is
he's very very careful about what he
says uh-huh and and he's very systematic
and you know I find I find that
inspiring but I have to agree with you
that there's there's a kind of force
lacking sometimes yeah and which
Peterson obviously has he has this kind
of charisma right even though his
message is much more simple there's
there's a forcefulness there which
people seem to be afraid of yeah
because Jordan peterson is phallic and
he appeals to say 23 year old men right
I don't see I think if you only stay
with a favoritest discourse which i
think is half of it anyway that's I'm
not I'm not against anything from our
cassettes or GaAs but I think it's only
delivering her
package now and that half of the package
is like it was with young too that would
be very popular with the spiritual
ladies right so women over 50 will love
this a lot but you know and it will be
spirituality they cannot hurt too they
can foster the children accordingly
whatever but if you if you don't have a
worldview that includes the energy the
raw sexual energy of young men you lost
it mmm you still haven't you still
haven't appeal to the entire audience
you you still haven't understood what
you must do you still haven't understood
the phallic must also exist not only the
magical as we call it the magical the
caretaking the the foundation you know
the magical the thing that pushes you
forward and scares you if you don't
follow if you don't move will drop you
right that's not some magical attitude
the phallic attitude is the one that
says that oh we gotta go somewhere and
we're gonna get to paradise or whatever
we call it we're gonna get somewhere our
women will give birth nine months from
now that's the ultimate form of phallic
mission so the phallic mission sets out
where we need to go and it's determined
to get there and it has a direction it's
a vision Gold direction and then
strategy how you implement that are all
within the phallic realm and you just
exist yeah none of this exists in the
current North America discourse and
actually that what you just said those
those things aim goal a direction etc is
kind of that's Peterson's essential
message right that's where he's been and
that's what nobody else is is kind of
saying everyone's kind of saying
emptiness and everyone's kind of saying
Buddhism and everyone's kind of saying
you know everyone's everyone's sort of
traumatized by the 20th century and yep
how's it hard stallion has a hard time
really to say okay we have to go here
because they're afraid of all the
dangers of totalitarianism you know
raising okay they're missing Marx so
Marx yeah cuz Marx is heroic just like
Newton look first question heed to ask
yourself when you start starting Karl
Marx in reading today is that why did he
write at all
since you had rose soul before him well
rosso inspired the French Revolution and
Marx was anti torso because he saw with
the French Revolution led and he
considered to be a bushwa revolution
what he deeply meant with that is that
it wasn't a genuine revolution it was
merely a symptom or a reaction to
another revolution that went on and
we've always in our work later you know
20 years later pointed out the printing
press was thrilled evolution in 1450 the
new revolution in terms memetics in
terms of ideas was of course the cards I
think therefore I am
that's 1632 so you have a real
revolution 40 or 50 you have a new idea
in 1632 which led to the European
enlightenment that led to the French
Revolution in 1789 before the French
Revolution Rousseau was the most widely
read author in France he was incredibly
popular and Rousseau basically said that
you're gonna take your grievances
against power with you out in the
streets and and you're gonna throw out
the old power and install some new kind
of power but without direction so when
people today are saying we're just gonna
sit in a group and talk endlessly and
something with a merge out of that and
that emergence will solve our problems
that incredibly naive and they're only
repeating a mistake that rose saw
pointed out in the 18th century in 18th
century France which actually led to a
bloody mess so we have to be careful
here I mean yes we are terrified of
another Hitler we're terrified of
another Stalin but as certicates that I
pointed out in digital libido or last
book we pointed out that it's quite easy
actually understand what Hitler and
Stalin got the power they did because
they were fake phalluses their own
authentic and you know the fake phallus
by his heart when he tries to unify you
with everybody else through hatred okay
so this is a strong like this is a
disagreement with Peterson like in terms
of you know what is the cause of all
this right for him it's for him Marxism
is a kind of leveling out of everything
you know everyone being kind of the same
he's not a more is more than lousy
Marxist and there's this rumor
it's even worse than that the irony is
the Jordan Peterson and Camilla Padma
are Marxists you just said what I've
been when I would I've sort of been
thinking for a while that the the
revolution of the proletariat right
that's kind of what a Peterson is doing
and this might kind of explain his
intimacy like with Marx and his also his
the fact that he's made Marx he's he's
not attacking Marx he's attacking a fake
version of Marxism popular in American
colleges so when Americans talk about
Marxism you have to ask them have you
actually studied Marx because most of
never have and it turns out they're only
quoting or referring to Marx in a second
or a third generation version of it
which is gone through American colleges
and things and they're actually talking
about Russell without understanding the
fundamental difference between gross oil
Marx and when Marx wrote at all and why
wrote aggressively against or so you
have to understand that Marx is heroic
so Marx does the same thing as Nietzsche
did nietzsche looks to an individual an
aristocrat he's cartesian in that sense
that's his problem
he's a cartesian but he looks at the
cartesian individual as a hero
that's the aristocrat anita Marx does
the same thing but he looks at the group
the tribe that's why I'm a Marxist than
one interested in Marx today because to
understand the current digital
subcultures and what will emerge out of
them we need to study Marx and
understand what a proletariat really is
Marx essentially saying that capitalism
is fine it's the best thing we've
entered so far but sooner or later
people will figure out a capitalism
actually works ok because there will be
more enlightened than the capitalist
they will beat the shit out of the
capitalist it is a form it's a form of
complete enlightenment the Marx is going
for and we call this proletariat netic
rats today that was our first book
twenty years ago the netic rats are the
realization of the marxist proletariat
and they're gonna take over rule the
world because of digital
so I just want to stop either because
when I talk to people who claim to be
Marxists they don't say that usually
usually they they say that there has to
be the socialism you know and and that
this will lead to communism and you know
and they complain about the elite all
the time you know and you're kind of
saying the opposite so yeah I'm artists
your your your version of Marxism is so
radically different than than the kind
of popular version of Marxism that
there's that's out there it's hard to
even have you know no okay but okay
Brandon O'Neil in the UK Aleksandr bard
in Sweden were European and we're
sitting at her screaming at the top of
our lungs can you please read Marx to
begin with to understand Marx because we
can't throw Marx out if you throw up
marks right now we thrown out the only
guy who told us there would be a class a
superior class that would lead us and
they could inspire the rest of humanity
at the stage where we're at now which is
good okay and that's where I want to go
I want to I want to I want you to talk
about the working class because I think
part of what's missing here and part of
what we're talking about here is this
working class right and what you know
and that's maybe Marx's insight is into
the working class right so what's the
value of the working class rule you know
yeah but let's stay with class and come
back to class later let's just go back
to Jordan Peterson here where we started
and he saw a stern quote here he is not
in himself
phallic base pointing out the value of
fellows in his unique still in North
American doing that and that's why he's
the only one of all these new great
voices coming out of North America the
only one has appealed to the young it
appealed to young men especially it's
been George Peterson after the order
finishes tour he's apparently rehab
right now god bless him hope it gets out
of there as quickly as possible we need
him but
but besides Jordans tour all the other
guys he known so far coming out of this
sort of intellectual dark web or deep
web whatever you want to call it are
North America are basically post Jordan
Free Riders Jordan is the only ones
appeal to young men I think that speaks
volumes and and um not only is a
charismatic and pedagogical which is
part of his success but he's also
pointing out the value here of phallus
and if you try to ignore phallus by
saying that we must start having utopia
missions which is for example for variks
stance then you're a really dangerous
territory that's way more dangerous than
reaching out for utopian vision wait a
minute Peterson is very anti utopian has
as well what he doesn't even know that
he's is harassed him right so you you do
bound to found certain self
contradictions with Jordan Peterson
they're different Jordan's here but I
would say the quote I started with today
that exposes Jordan Peterson so asterism
so as soon ism is the only religion ever
that is phallic and modest at the same
time that's why I converted I converted
Zoroastrianism and started building my
philosophy on it and I'm gonna explore
it deeper in the coming books because
unless you have a phallic Manas
worldview
you're lost number one the world is
modest it's not dualist that means you
can disqualify all the Abrahamic
religions from day one the second thing
is that once you accept that the world
is modest it's one substance within huge
amount of attributes that's how the
world operates that's been OSA once you
accepted that and you start looking at
what kind of narratives do we have today
it turns out the narratives we have
today are very infantile or they're very
metrical at worse their infant type and
worse they just say we're all little
kids and we all should feel sorry for
ourselves and we should throw our
grievances in the open and attack
anybody doesn't give us exactly what one
at all times it's like a bunch of babies
looking for a new tit to suck that is
the dominant mode in contemporary
society so when you look at the
existential crises DeJohn for Varkey all
these guys are pointing out the direct
sexual understanding
of the current crisis to say that we
have an infantilized society because of
the welfare state because of consumer
society working class is being sedated
and people are basically just consuming
and screaming at the top of the lungs
when they don't get the tit mm-hmm it's
been like that for a long time I mean
it's gotten worse and worse it's started
the night worse it's starting the 1950s
gotten worse and the reason why starting
the 1950s was that we came out of the
Second World War in 1945 we blow it up
in a Tomic bomb without Hitler install
it so and we also needed to decolonize
the world so colonization coming out of
Europe and the conquering or at least
three continents and the colonization of
the world then Hitler installed in the
top of that of course that gave us kind
of a bad idea what follows was right
you know the fake phalluses has had
their day this was the Golden Age of the
fake phallus really you know so when we
end up with 1945 of course um we don't
want to know the world war we know that
both the United States and eventually
the Soviet Union have atomic bombs so we
like them to stay in their place and not
blow up more bombs what we did though
was that we created this idea that we
could have an ultimate evil and called
Nazism and because in ultimate evil
we don't ultimately the sense that it's
it's evil in a metaphysical sense it
cannot be understood it's just pure evil
yeah just massively the proud that is
that anybody who wasn't a Nazi anybody
of any kind there was not basically the
entire population we're good
so we've had a celebration of mediocrity
on a massive scale in culture since 1945
yeah and in this letter in 1952 the
celebration of the teenager because once
you start celebrating mediocrity in a
culture why even make the effort in
becoming otherwise yeah well like what
why ever put a you know a price on on
life experience what why would that be
valuable no the only thing a solid is to
be young and sexy and to be something
everyone wants to sleep with
that that starts with James Dean Marilyn
Monroe the 1950s and the export of the
American teenager to the rest of world
as a human ideal you know this is what
we lived with for the past 50 years and
when we speak about the existence of
crisis we have today if you don't
understand the mistakes we also made
after 1945 dialectical mistakes you made
and we ended up in the other dustbin we
just we just we got away from the ditch
of Hitler and Stalin and we ended up
with the other ditch instead which is
the real scientist that's why we're full
of social justice warriors and
self-proclaimed saviors and all kinds of
things out there because we're terrified
for somebody stepping forward with a
properly utopian vision you know
somebody have stepped forward a property
utopia we said we're gonna get there you
know that would change the game entirely
and I don't mean Elemis going to Mars to
the rakatans like that that's just a
little boy dreaming about being a
messiah but if the Messianic doesn't
return to the world of philosophy we're
completely lost mmm and this is where I
want to challenge former key I wanted to
challenge two guys out there and all I'm
saying I'm just pointing out none of you
guys will get the young guys on the moon
mm-hmm because they'd be like let's do
here in Europe so the way I get the
young guys on the move is through a
messianic vision yes and that is an
equation that is what we need yeah yeah
and that's yes and that's why I turned
to Zoroastrianism and and Mithraism
which was the religion of the Roman
Empire which is another verse or
asterism I turn to the Irani heritage
I'm starting right now in detail you
know I've discussed it for the Sufism is
key here house or a schism eventually
influenced Islam Judaism absolutely it's
an enormous cross-pollination between
Buddhism Azure asterism it's the most
fruitful collaboration of ideas ever
he's the meeting between Buddhism Azure
autism they both have origins Buddhism
probably originated in Afghanistan and
later walked down into northern India as
well as to do some original Central
Asian eventually ended up in Iran and
both these two religions have cross
pollinated with each other for hundreds
of years or even thousands of years and
it's in between the two that I think we
have the best
case today for what I call the
numerology no mythology is the story of
how we need to get humanity on the move
and everybody has to follow mm-hmm so
this movement then we need to restart a
kickstart to get out of the currency
obesity pandemics and everything
literally this movement is best led by
Soros the perspective sonic perspective
but with a fervor key in these other
guys that are Buddhists are coming into
the picture and do great work is that we
also need the magical stones bones yeah
yes exactly but if you only take the
Buddhists magical perspective you end up
working on the container again and again
again and you don't consider the content
it's a bit like the current climate out
there you know we love the rebel wisdom
guys in the UK and they're also involved
with this the art of conversation
like if you only had a better
understanding of a conversation can
deliver magically this Lucius would
appear there's why they talk about
emergence or something like we got a
city groups and authentically relate to
each other a little circling authenticly
relate to each other and listen to each
other and out of that suddenly all the
solutions will come forward that is not
going to happen it's still good it's
just not the whole story and it's
dangerous exporting company it could
become let's say the devouring mother
what will you say you must not have
utopia vision and you sit endlessly in
conversations with people to try to find
solutions to problems that you're
certainly stuck in that environment and
it's you just want to be comforted yeah
probably
exactly so look at motives and that's
the other thing that's lacking in for
various analysis is that he talks about
the Gnostics talks about different
spiritual ambitions in an almost naive
way like if all people who claimed to be
spiritual were genuine about it no
they're not the vast majority of people
who claim to be spiritual are only
making a pose again you need Marx to
understand this when Marx
distances himself from the French
Revolution as being bourgeois
he means it
sort of demeaning way like it's
petit-bourgeois it's only the salons
anyway
they attacked her side you know they
killed the people in Versailles with the
guillotine but they only repeated the
same thing so what was tragedy
Versailles became farce in Paris the
parish ins residence yeah yeah so the
parishes eventually became exactly like
Forsyte exactly like today's society
when people are posing with the way they
describe themselves would the way they
express themselves to talk about
totality they talk about etiquette it's
an obsession with if he could only find
the right conversation and respect each
other authentically relate to each other
and use the right wordings when we speak
so it's the massive focus on tonality
netiquette and what's completely
forgotten it's the content mm-hmm but
what what the hell you gonna talk about
that okay okay so it's like you're
arranging a party and you you're setting
the tables and you're putting the wine
glasses and the coffee cups forward and
and you're old you're talking about
where we're gonna put the napkins where
we're gonna put the knives to the four
to it's like you walk around all day
long four hours away then you put a
McDonald on the plate
no not even that not even that there is
nothing on the plate this is my point
with current North American or
anglo-saxon discourse it doesn't dare to
even confront itself with the fact that
there's nothing on the plate mmm-hmm if
you look at all these the hundreds of
hours you're probably plowed through so
if I you know I've read my philosophy
but I'm also seriously interested in
what's going on and I find it amazing
there's a whole new anglo-saxon based
seeing the take spirituality seriously
the ones politics to go spiritual but it
doesn't dare to speak its true nature
it doesn't dare to understand where it
fails I think it's the reason for that
is something I think the reason for that
is I think it's what you're saying
I think that's why the Ken Wilber
movement became so decadent and all of
these movements sort of lost lost their
original you know energy because
the they weren't they weren't they
weren't daring to - to be a bit
antagonist ik against the culture okay
say say you walk into Versailles okay
you you were invited you were lucky you
got a VIP ticket to the VIP salon okay
what is what are people obsessed with in
that environment say you go to an award
Scala what are people to assess with
that environment hierarchy social
hierarchy she's like who's the top of
things and who's at the bottom of things
who was just briefly sneaked in right
and who's like the big star like who's
the star and all the posting that's
going on in the room this is this is
Marx's critique of the furniture all the
posting is going on in the room is all
about social hurricane what did Ken
Wilber do he created spiral dynamics
what does he say he says that on top of
everything is Ken Wilber and beneath ken
world were there the people that are
less enlightened than Ken Wilber and the
yet may different colors to the weary
hey Ken Wilber is a essentially a
ranging of her sigh party this is
essentially arranging a party where some
people are higher than others more noble
than those because they know better and
this is incredibly petit-bourgeois
incredibly middle class and again that's
why you need to go back to Mars which
Jordan Peter Seneca Mill Park that
actually do because they go back to the
working-classes command pod Lois talks
about the Parikh and women who live in
the great and we're mothers of five and
the fee status and the guts in us they
had I do the same thing that is a
Marxist approach so you go back to the
working classes and then you just
compare the working classes to this sort
of little middle class drama I would
spiral dynamics and different caller
tags and who's more enlightened and it
looks ridiculous
no will barian pyramid it's just it's
just what the fuck is that
no no there are no callers of
enlightenment there are no different
levels of enlightenment
you're not more enlightened just because
you vote for Hillary Clinton instead of
Donald Trump forget it you know and and
Jordan Peterson points this out come
upon us the same thing so for me still
the way forward towards the phallic in
North America goes through them but they
still they still at least Peterson still
points out
talks about the need for let's say
higher gift of confidence right yes
that's right that is important right yes
that's right it's not just not a
hierarchy of beautiful souls or exactly
exactly you learned that from me that's
Hegel's hegel hegel what's our cut Hey
well I think that's why we're looking
for that the working class is because
they're not beautiful souls there's a
vitality of just the fact that they have
to survive every day that makes them
more real than all of this abstraction
and all of this except nationalization
exactly so will you take a Marxist
approach us say for example digital in
Silicon Valley that being said of con
values at the end of the road Silicon
Valley is just capitalists today and
we're gonna see a Marxist proletariat
rise up against them and that's well
what a child for example through East
African India where I work a lot these
days
and I see these kids to pick up their
smartphones and pick up the laptops and
they said a program and they make a
little funny things they can use their
they're not hyped the way things are of
Silicon Valley they don't have the
billions of the Holliston venture
capital if they like that all they are
the new proletariat they are the genuine
netic rats they're gonna change the
world and they gonna use it it'll change
it and they might use platforms that
were born in Silicon Valley to do it
fair enough
Silicon Valley is certainly part of the
game but Seneca Valley to me today is
exactly the way
Marx described the French Revolution
this is not digital this is just a
precursor to digital this is the
middle-class version of digital but the
real working-class version of digital
still has to emerge it's not there yet
but once it emerges and it's there
that's gonna be the genuine revolution
so that's why you could call me digital
Marxist if you like I'm sure Brandon
O'Neil would subscribe to that Keith
ounce the Pearson has just written a
book where he compares nee-chan rules so
genius ok read that book there's a lot
of stuff going on a philosopher act I
will be visiting the great thinkers of
19th century Europe Hegel Freud
Nietzsche even Darwin is in there and
we're revisiting them and we're finding
strength in that and we can now properly
analyze the current situation
and to properly analyze it for Varkey
and these guys have done a tremendous
job on one half of that they worked on
the container they worked on the context
when I talked to John I said you do
great work because John for variks work
is basically to put up the context first
in an Aristotelian sense into which the
right proper gratitude can then be poor
I think he says that too I mean I think
that's his he doesn't want to have a
grand narrative he wants to sort of give
give people the tools to do that
themselves no he he's afraid of utopia
visas he's afraid of the phallus mm-hmm
he admits that episode 39 40 let's see
so far they did that yeah
okay the froggie afraid he's afraid of
hegelian romanticism coming back and
then and then you know and sort of
sweeping you know well you know what
let's put it this way very
straightforward it
what for Varghese doing is basically
telling you you're sitting in egypt and
you're a slave and it's basically
telling that if moses or Aaron walks by
tomorrow since we're going to go to the
promised land don't follow them that's
what he's saying
okay that's what he's safe that's where
you end up when you don't have a phallus
you don't have a vision of how you're
gonna get out of your slavery and hope
how the fuck are you gonna talk about
getting out of an existential crisis
unless the exercise itself changes so we
need to get out of Egypt so to get out
of the Egypt which is takes essential
crisis to get out of that and walk to
the promised land somebody's got to come
forward and say okay I or the people
onwards are the Messianic and we're
gonna lead you into the promised on
who's gonna come with us and a small
minority people will then step out of
their slavery and said okay we go
forward each one of those people is in
each and Oberman yeah and the rest of
them are sort of fake messiahs wait wait
let me finish no yeah that's the you
know but each one of the slaves who
steps up and comes with the Messiah
walks out of Egypt is in each and
Oberman
that is fundamentally
Newman's on his own but together as a
group they are the proletariat
that's Marxist point but Marx says is
that the proletariat will lead and go
forward to the promised land this is
what the utopian visions were always
about so you need to Riyadh and
understand that without the FEL equation
how the heck are we gonna get out of the
extension of crisis for variks response
is probably something more like well if
we have little gatherings in the
evenings in Egypt and the slaves sit
together at night when they're finally
off work and have a little time to
themselves and talk and listen to each
other
something will emerge out of that well
that will set you free
well you haven't left Egypt have you
you're still in Egypt so if you're still
in Egypt nothing will emerge out of
those conversations especially not from
people who sit and talk all day long and
meditate all day long and you're golden
long for all I care but never study
anything and have no idea what they're
talking about so you're gonna end up
with a new anglo-saxon spiritual
discourse when ladies come along few men
and they sit and talk for hours and
hours and hours and wait for something
to emerge out of that and all this kind
of merge is more coffee cops a little
candy nothing else there's nothing
visionary about that at all yes it's
good to learn to listen it's good to
authentically relate to other people
just like it's good to meditate it's
good to do yoga but at the end of the
day you got to read some damn fucking
books and you got to go into deep study
you gotta understand history better you
get it better be more learn and then you
can on work for Varrick is done which
created the container you can on top of
that when you learn the things the
fabric is teaching on top of that you
must look for the final equation without
it you're lost
so this is where current North American
anglo-saxon discourse and doesn't hit it
my hope is the Jordan gets this once
it's out of rehab because he's at least
a sore ass Jim and he clearly defines
himself as such and the reek when he
says that makes order out of chaos this
is Jordan Peters uncle who he believes
in what makes order out of chaos
well order doesn't self organize out of
chaos
octave chaos reaches a certain point
where a certain amount of
self-organization happens otherwise
order would not exist at all but what we
do as human beings is that we tame and
domesticate the little self-organization
nature provides
that's called culture so we take
whatever nature has self-organized and
then we make culture out of it by taming
and domesticating it and the process of
taming and domesticating requires utopia
vision in architecture that's called the
plan the architecture has made a drawing
that's very interesting what you were
saying before about the fellows vision
as well so what what all these guys are
doing and I'm speaking from the heart to
John for vark and the other guys are
doing it all they're doing is that
they're still talking about we're
getting all the building materials
together and then somehow mystically a
skyscraper will come out of that it will
not to build a skyscraper you need to
know the science of building materials
you need to have all the right building
materials from wherever you need to get
them you need to get them and you need
to build everything properly like parts
and then parts being put together into a
hole and then eventually you can build
the damn skyscraper the skyscraper does
not suddenly materialize out of meetings
for people respectfully authentically
relate to each other talking is not
engineering ok what's coming up for me
here Alexander is I was thinking about I
was thinking about a young young people
and and and you're and again going back
to what you said at the beginning about
23 year olds and young men and yeah
vitality of that are not being important
and also the missing other pieces is
elders right those are the two men yes
that's great with hvar kit by the way he
talks about wisdom a lot so but wisdom
it's not something you get by getting a
new collar tag from ken Woolever please
you know wisdom another word for wisdom
is life experience you go elderly people
I did that my whole life I love sitting
down with my 85 year old mom
just listen to her and her life
experience she's an older version of
myself she's been through a lot more
than I have and the older people are
they're the reason why we survive for
three generations rather than just to is
to have access to grandfather's
grandmother's older people who have
wisdom wisdom is that they've been
around you know and they don't have a
ego problem any longer they're not
driven by any narcissism they just they
just laugh at those homes just ya know
I've been around quite a lot the only
thing that's valuable to you when you're
75 years old
is that your life experience has a value
to those who are younger mm-hmm that's a
mentorship as much the video you put up
of James Gillian Eames speaking about
how you know the older person loses
doesn't the kind of yeah all that's all
that you know you know bullshit of
trying to to be something and his
character and kind of emerges like we
love yes he'll might have character and
and younger people in their 20s they
have some character but you know life
has to kind of break you to have
character I think exactly okay you you
are and you are hopefully an archetype
when you're younger you have a primary
and a secondary archetype you and I've
talked about this before the primary
archetype which is the things you'd do
with East that other people are
impressed with and second or get up the
things you could do if somebody had to
do it know what else be around okay
that's what you do when you're younger
you you learn your archetype and you
become the kind of personality the kind
of man or woman or anything in between
that you should be but the character
exactly Hillman is wonderful we love
Jane so much you know and in a way when
I recommend people to read Zachary Stein
today I point out the sacristy and he's
like a contemporary James Hillman James
Hillman is the best possible American
jeonggyun psychologist you could find
like and he he he wrote formatively they
are gratefully there are clips of him
doing interviews in the 97 is available
online so check out James Hillman and
what he's saying he's a really wise man
but when he talks about wisdom he talks
about it like the character you get with
old age cuz you've lived a full life and
and you have experience and that
character
II swear you speak from so this is also
the other PC says that is you meet all
the monsters right by the time you're
old you've met all the monsters so so
which I think it's kind of interesting
cuz I think young people haven't met the
monsters yet so they they have a lot of
pride and they have a lot of ego and and
they think they know something but they
haven't quite met the monsters yet so
they they can't speak with real
authority yeah yeah great descriptions
Hillman is brilliant so snotty James
Solman dies out there if you're
interested in the border between
psychology and philosophy James Hoban
it's a perfect source to go to great
great guy but this this being scared of
the fellows thing that's going on at the
moment it's um it's a typical
contemporary phenomenon we need to get
out of that sure we need to approach the
phallic and we need to understand that
without the masonic we're lost
and what's both terrifying here and also
is of course possibly the solution to
our current problems is that in my work
at least you probably agree with me the
messianic is essentially what we gonna
tell the machine to do once
technological intelligence comes into
the picture so in this symbiotic
intelligence game woody to Roy by the
way talks a lot about this like we
haven't even begun to understand how
complex humans are she's beautiful with
that so if we need to Roy recommend it
again but oh the human Intel about
logical intelligence that we were
representing it speak shaped like humans
right biological intelligence BI is one
thing the other one is technological
intelligence TI i prefer that to machine
it is technological it it is it is
fundamentally in intelligence to support
the biological intelligence of humans
it's this sound like that you know for
the foreseeable future will be and the
order we will give to TI developers is
that you gotta make sure from day one
that technological intelligence supports
humanity and it supports humanity
in the way that would you manatee cannot
create with needs has to be created
somewhere else and the ultimate version
of that is the Masonic so you know if we
need to be saved and apparently we need
to and we cannot find the savior among
ourselves or we've killed him or
something
then um the Savior has to be the machine
or at least it has to be the symbiotic
intelligence and the collaboration
between man and machine again it says
Humanity can I stop you there for a sec
um yeah I think this is an ocean and
another one of your ear notions that is
would be very offensive to people to
think that a machine would which would
save us right because because people
would like to think that we have agency
to to saber ourselves we don't we don't
have no capacity we don't know that
capacity we don't have the intellectual
capacity to save ourselves and I mean I
speak as a philosopher you know you know
at the end of the day my job is not to
be the savior no I'm still Doron
Peterson and I are in the same mode we
are don't the Baptist's here looking for
the Messiah to step forwards we can
baptize and we can do this job the the
Messianic here is what will save
humanity out of the existential crisis
okay okay okay can you go into that in
detail like what is the contain the
nuclear bomb so they don't blow us up
and you know climate threat get that
recent issues yeah yeah no it's not evil
at all these are very concrete problems
that need to be solved otherwise you
won't be around a hundred years from now
so to to solve these problems we need
the Masonic so the Masonic is
engineering the Masonic is architecture
but that's still strategy architectural
engineering is strategy its constructing
strategy and implementing strategy the
vision itself has to be written first
that we need the grand narrative and
without that phallic vision that dares
to be phallic were lost and that's what
goes back to the history of ideas
discovered where did phallic start from
and of course there were failures there
too
Jason race or your Johnny's written a
brilliant book right now called Iranian
Leviosa
he is an old drug guy let's admit that
but he's a great historian and he points
out that the different Persian empires
can teach us quite a lot Persia or Iran
he's the only part of the world that
actually gone through four different
empires at four different stages of
history they can be studied
comparatively to understand Empire as
something larger than nation and we need
Empire today because technology itself
is imperial technology service global an
imperial global Empire already exists
it's called the Internet Protocol and so
to understand where we can't go wrong
with FAL accretion if you want to
understand that we not only have Hitler
and Stalin for example we have tons of
ruthless barbarian emperors throughout
history we bloody like hell especially
in Asia I think it teaches quite a lot
where the father goes wrong we can learn
for example that when the phallic leader
stays for too long and gets too corrupt
he becomes the tyrant can also learn
from history that will the chief chin of
the priests are unified and become the
same person we get in tyrant ok Sun God
and the rain God must never be the same
guy because if it's the same guy God we
have a problem so we can learn about
tyranny we can start of history journey
we can start the history of
authoritarianism we can start in the
history of monotheism or whatever you
want to call it but anything that only
has one solution to all problems it's
problematic because we need parole for
something to work in the long run and be
sustainable so plurality has to be part
of the messianic this time that doesn't
contradict the fact that is messianic
mmm okay so the Messianic is essentially
the goal of where we're going and the
direction that will take us out of the
current crisis and then will put us on
the moon so we leave the state we're
stuck in